Muir mss. III, 1928-1996 LMC 2287
Lilly Library
Muir mss. III
1928-1996
Lilly Library
Muir, Percy H. (Percy Horace), 1894-1979
LMC 2287
3 linear feet 2 Boxes
The Muir mss. III, 1928-1979, consist of correspondence and writings of bookseller Percy Muir, relating largely to his bookselling firm Elkin Mathews.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 2002
Biographical Note
Percy Muir was associated with the antiquarian bookselling firm, Elkin Mathews, Ltd. from 1930 until his death in 1979. Founded in 1885 by Charles Elkin Mathews, the business began in the Cathedral Close at Exeter but moved to London in 1887 when Elkin Mathews and John Lane went into partnership. Within a very few years publishing became the principle interest of the firm, now Elkin Mathews and John Lane Ltd., with retail sales of books, old and new, taking a secondary place. The two men parted company in 1894 and Mathews, although continuing to publish, returned to a greater concentration on bookselling. He died in 1922. A.W. Evans, ex–curate, ex–journalist, and himself a collector and customer of Elkin Mathews, acquired the business as a going concern from Mathews' widow. Percy Muir joined the firm, as a partner, in January 1930, becoming managing director in 1939. It was under his stewardship that the firm moved from London during the German blitz to Blakeney, Norfolk.
Percy Muir was president of the Antiquarian Booksellers Association in Britain from 1945-1947, and chaired the first conference of the International League of Antiquarian Booksellers (ILAB) in 1947. He became president of the ILAB from 1950-1952 and was subsequently elected the first Life President of Honor. The author of several bibliographies and books on book collecting, as well as an autobiography: Minding My Own Business (Chatto & Windus, 1956), he also made frequent contributions to Colophon, Library, and various bibliographical journals such as Bookman's Journal. He was also a founder and member of the editorial board of Book Collector.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Muir's correspondence and writings relating to his career with Elkin Mathews, Ltd., as well as manuscripts and typescripts of his "Further Reminiscences" series in The Book Collector.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following order: I. Correspondence; II. Book Collector; III. Coke, Gerald; IV. Flower, Newman; V. Ogden, C.K.; VI. Wilson, Caroll A.; VII. Writing; VIII. Printed Materials; IX. Mischellaneous.
Related Materials
See Muir mss., Muir mss. II, Muir mss. IV, and Muir mss. V, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Booksellers and bookselling; E. Mathews (Firm)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Adelman, Seymore, Jan. 7, 1964 - Jan. 24, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, Reginald, Aug. 5, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antrim, Earl, Mar. 5, 1959 - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arlott, John, Apr. 21, 1961 - Nov. 20, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bain, Lain, 1953 - May 1, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Batey, Charles, July 22, 1969 - Aug. 3, 1969
  - Boudin, Fernand, Feb. 24, 1969 - Nov. 17, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Blanck, Jacob (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Butler, R.A.B., Mar. 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carter, Harry, Oct. 9, 1962 - Sept. 11, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Carter, Will Chambers, Sept. 5, 1961 - Nov. 23, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chamot, Mary, May 5, 1963 - May 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Copper, Winfred and Mark Cohen, Jan. 31, 1957 - Sept. 4, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Crook, Arthur, Mar. 2, 1964 - July 6, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Crowe, Stanley, May 7, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Crutchley, Brooke, Jan. 30, 1964 - Feb. 14, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Curle, Richard, Aug. 6, 1963 - Oct. 3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Custard, Joyce, Jul. 9, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - De Morode, Baroness Frederick Derra, June 24, 1964 - June 2, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Denison, Alan, Aug. 3, 1960 - Nov. 27, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Notes Etc., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Edinger, George, Nov. 3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Edwards, Harold, July 3, 1959 - Nov. 11, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Elwell, Bob, Jan. 3, 1967 - May 7, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fales, DeCousey, Oct. 25, 1963 - Nov. 28, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Feather, J.P., Mar. 9, 1976 - Mar. 22, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fleming, Ian, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Flowers, Desmond, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Foxon, David, Aug. 13, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fraser, Antonia, July 9, 1964 - July 20, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gathorne-Hardy, Eddie, Apr. 28, 1969 - Aug. 10, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gathorne-Hardy, Robert, 1932 - Mar. 31, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gawsorth, John, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gill, Evan, Jan. 23, 1959 - June 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gooden, Stephen, May 7, 1945 - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Greene, Roger and John Hadfield, June 17, 1954 - Oct. 28, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hamill, Frances, Jan. 16, 1958 - Sept. 10, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hanover, P.M., Oct. 28, 1959 - Nov. 4, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Harling, Robert, Jan. 24, 1959 - Jan. 9, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Harrison, Richard, June 3, 1959 - July 7, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hauler, Charles, Mar. 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hassall, John, July 17, 1960. Aug. 26, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hilton, James, Apr. 27, 1935 - Mar. 16, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hirsch, Paul, Jan. 19, 1941 - May 10, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Lists, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Notes and Recipts, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hopkins, Kenneth, Jan. 19, 1959 - Dec. 3, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Hopkins on Cecil, May 28, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Howe, Ellie, Feb. 3, 1959 - Dec. 22, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hyde, Montgomery, Mar. 16, 1965 - May 7, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Jackson, W.A., June 18, 1964 - June 22, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Kaynes, Geoffrey, May 16, 1961 - Jan. 4, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Keynes, Quinton and John Lewis, Feb. 26, 1964 - June 1, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Lewis, W.S., Jan. 7, 1945 - Sept. 8, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Lillicrap, Charles, Oct. 3, 1966 - Dec. 16, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Links, J.G., Sept. 1968 - Oct. 15, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Lion and Unicorn Press, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Lister, Raymond, May 13, 1964 - Dec. 31, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Low, David, Jan. 3, 1964 - Oct. 18, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - McLean, Ruari, Mar. 9, 1959 - Dec. 29, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Malson, Jack and William Maxwell, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Metzdorf, Robert, Jan. 16, 1964 - Apr. 4, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Meyerstein, E.H.W., Dec. 20, 1942 - Apr. 24, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Meynell, Francis, Sept. 9, 1967 - July 15, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Middleton, Bernard, Jan. 29, 1964 - July 18, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Moran, James, Jan. 29, 1964 - July, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Morrison, Stanley, Dec. 2, 1959 - Oct. 4, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Morpurge, J.E. And J. Mosley, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Moult, Thomas, Jan. 22, 1959 - May 25, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Moulton, Mary, Aug. 14, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Mairhead, Arnold, Jan. 20, 1964 - Nov. 17, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Munby, A.N.L., Apr. 12, 1958 - June 20, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Nebehay, Christian, Nov. 10, 1971 - June 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Newbolt, Peter, Sept. 10, 1964 - Oct. 7, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Nowell-Smith, Simon, Sept. 10, 1940 - July 29, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Oates, J.C.T., Oct. 14, 1955 - Feb. 7, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Opie, Peter, June 29, 1965 - Dec. 14, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Osborn, James, Jan. 31, 1959 - May 11, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Pitz, Henry, Feb. 22, 1959 - June 6, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Plover, William and Lawrence Clark Powell (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Quayle, Eric, Gordon Ray and Geoffrey Rhodes, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Randall (James II Memoirs), June 4, 1954 - July 4, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Roth-Wolfe, "Lotte", Jan. 11, 1961 - Mar. 8, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Rothenstein, William, Apr. 11, 1959 - Dec. 3, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Russell, Leonard and Siegfried Sasson, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Schatzki, Walter, Sept. 25, 1967 - Oct. 26, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Schauer, G.K., Mar. 18, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Schmoller, Hans, June 20, 1961 - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Schwartz, Jacob, Mar. 20, 1959 - Mar. 22, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Shepard, Leslie, Dec. 24, 1969 - Jan. 1, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Sieveking, Lance, Sept.14, 1962 - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Smite, Logan Pearsall, Jan. 19, 1934 - Nov. 23, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Sparrow, John, Jan.2, 1959 - Jan. 7, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Sperison, Albert, Jan. 22, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Steinberg, S.H., May 16, 1966 - June 26, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Stephens, James, James Stern, Christine Stewart and Reynolds Sonte, 1928-1976 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Strays, Ralph, Julian Symons and Francis Thompson, 1929-1952 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Tschichold, Jan, Apr. 6, 1963 - May 21, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Viets, Henry, Jan. 24, 1962 - Jan. 29, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Watson, Rowland (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Weil, Ernst, Dec. 21, 1954 - Nov. 14, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Welch, D'Alle, Oct. 9, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Wells, James, Dec. 4, 1959 - Dec. 31, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Wolpe, Berthold, Oct. 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 105)
- Book Collector (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Nov. 29, 1944 - Feb. 10, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Correspondence, Nov. 9, 1971 - Nov. 14, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Barker, Nicholas, June 21, 1966 - Nov. 22, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Photocopies of Letters, May 4, 1955 - June 28, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Photocopies - Misc., records, statements, and writings (Box 2, Folder 110)
- Coke, Gerald (Box 2)
  - Coke to Muir, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Muir to Coke, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Flower, Newman (Box 2)
  - Music Collection Correspondence, Dec. 12, 1957 - June 15, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Music Collection - Misc., Investors, Appraisals (Box 2, Folder 115)
- Ogden, C.K. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Lists, Misc. Printed Materials, 1959-1996 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Dealer Notes (Box 2, Folder 117)
- Wilson, Carroll A. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Lists, Notes (Box 2, Folder 118)
- Writing (Box 2)
  - Titles (Box 2)
    - "Book Hunting Before and Behind the Iron Curtain" (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - "February 14 and all That" (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - "Further Reminisces" part 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - "Further Reminisces" part 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - "The London Book Shop" (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - "Some Whys and Wheres of Book Collecting" (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - "Why Not Collect Ruth Peter" (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 2)
    - ABA/ILAD (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Bibliographies, Lists, etc. (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Dedication Copy of La Favorite de Donizeth, Dr. John's Bible & Prayer Book (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - English Private Presses (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Fragments (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - PM, The Traiters (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Reviews (Box 2, Folder 132)
- Printed Materials (Box 2)
  - Besterman, Theodore (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Diedericks, Lydia, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Koch, Rudolph (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Kurnitz, Harry (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Pollard, Grahm (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Sadler Circle (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 139)
- Mischellaneous (Box 2)
  - Weekly Report (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Booklets (Box 2, Folder 141)